Vassar Miller Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Vassar Miller Papers
1937-1992
Miller, Vassar
Houstonian Vassar Miller published ten volumes of poetry over the course of a literary career which spanned almost forty years, and was twice named poet laureate of Texas. The collection includes correspondence, manuscripts and typescripts of her poems, plays, and short stories, and materials pertaining to the editing and publication of the anthology Despite This Flesh.
17 boxes, 8409 leaves, 22 photographs, and 81 items; 9 linear feet
1987-003
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Biographical Note
Vassar Miller was born in Houston in 1924, the daughter of a prominent architect. She began writing as a child, composing on a typewriter due to the cerebral palsy which affected her speech and movement. She attended the University of Houston, receiving her B.A. and M.A. in English.
In 1956, Miller published her first volume of poetry, Adam's Footprint. Her poems, most of which dealt with either her strong religious faith or her experiences as a person with a disability, were widely praised for their rigorous formality, clarity, and emotional impact. In 1961 Miller was nominated for a Pulitzer Prize for her collection Wage War on Silence. Over the course of a literary career which spanned almost forty years, Miller published ten volumes of poetry in all. An outspoken advocate for the rights and dignity of the handicapped, Miller also edited a collection of poetry and short stories about persons with disabilities titled Despite This Flesh.
Miller received many awards and accolades for her poetry in her home state. Three of her books won the annual poetry prize of the Texas Institute of Letters. In 1982 and 1988 Miller was named Poet Laureate of Texas, and in 1997 she was named to the Texas Women's Hall of Fame by the Governor's Commission for Women.
Vassar Miller died in 1998.
Major Works:
If I Had Wheels or Love. Dallas, Tex.: Southern Methodist University Press, 1991.
(Editor). Despite This Flesh. Austin, Tex.: University of Texas Press, 1985.
Struggling to Swim on Concrete. New Orleans, La.: New Orleans Poetry Journal Press, 1984.
Selected and New Poems, 1950-1980. Austin, Tex.: Latitudes Press, 1981.
Approaching Nada. Houston, Tex.: Wings Press, 1977.
Small Change. Houston, Tex.: Wings Press, 1976.
If I Could Sleep Deeply Enough. New York: Liveright, 1974.
Onions and Roses. Middletown, Conn.: Wesleyan University Press, 1968.
My Bones Being Wiser. Middletown, Conn.: Wesleyan University Press, 1963.
Wage War on Silence. Middletown, Conn.: Wesleyan University Press, 1960.
Adam's Footprint. New Orleans, La.: New Orleans Poetry Journal, 1956.
Scope and Contents
The Vassar Miller Papers contain material pertaining to Miller's writings, career, and personal life, and materials pertaining to the editing and publication of the anthology Despite This Flesh. Materials range in date from circa 1937 to 1992, with most of the material falling between the years 1960 to 1986.
The series relating to Miller's own work and life contain correspondence, poems, short stories, plays, miscellaneous works, drafts and typescripts of published works, and material related to Miller's writing career. The Despite This Flesh series contain correspondence, material related to the preparation of the anthology, stories and poems which were considered for possible inclusion in the anthology, and drafts and proofs of the anthology.
Noteworthy correspondents whose letters or notes may be found in the collection include Larry McMurtry, Richard Hugo, Calvin Trillin, Anne Tyler, and James Wright. A brief partial autobiography of Vassar Miller can be found in Miscellaneous Works, and typescripts of interviews done with Vassar Miller may be found in the correspondence of Karla Hammond and the correspondence of Christopher Woods.
Two chapbooks, Small Change and Approaching Nada, two literary magazines, The Touchstone and Elizabeth, and one broadside, Open Question, have been removed from the manuscript collection and cataloged.
Special Collections also holds numerous signed copies of Miller's books, and Miller's personal collection of signed books by other poets.
Subjects (Persons)
Miller, Vassar; McMurtry, Larry
Subjects
People with disabilities -- Literary collections
Formats
Correspondence; Chapbooks; Photographs; Manuscripts
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Acquisition
This collection was purchased from Vassar Miller by the UH Libraries in 1987-1988 with the support of the Rockwell Fund and the Imperial Oil Company. Maud Lipscomb donated twenty 4×5″ black and white photographic prints which she took in 1985. Jon Schultz donated a program from the memorial service for Craig Gallagher.
Detailed Description
- Correspondence, (870 leaves, 4 items): (Box 1-2, Folder 1-25, 1-27)
  This series includes correspondence from editors, fellow writers, friends, and family members of Vassar Miller, and some from Miller to her correspondents. Major correspondents are Miller's Latitudes Press editor Bob Bonazzi, her New Orleans Poetry Journal Press editor Maxine Cassin, and her interviewer Karla Hammond. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the last name of the sender, then each sender's correspondence is arranged chronologically. Correspondence identified by first name only, or unidentified, is filed at the end of the series.
  - Misc. A (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Misc. B (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Robert (Bob) Bonazzi (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
  - Misc. C (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Maxine Cassin (Box 1, Folder 9-14)
  - Misc. D (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Misc. E (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Misc. F (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Misc. G (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Misc. H (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Karla Hammond (Box 1, Folder 20-23)
  - Misc. I (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Misc. J (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Misc. K (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bruce Kellner (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Misc. L (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Misc. M (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Vassar Miller, 1969-1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Vassar Miller, 1986-undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Misc. N (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Misc. O (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Misc. P (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Norman Holmes Pearson (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Misc. R (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Misc. S (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Misc. T (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - J.R. de la Torre Bueno (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Misc. U (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Misc. V (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Misc. W (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
  - Stuart Wright (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Misc. Y (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Misc. Z (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - First Names Only (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Unidentified (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Poems, (2329 leaves): (Box 3-6)
  Individual poems are arranged first chronologically, then alphabetically within each year. Undated poems are arranged alphabetically after the dated poems. These are followed by unpublished poetry manuscripts in chronological order, and rough drafts of poems in chronological order.
  - Poems, ca. 1937 (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
  - Poems, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Poems, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 10-14)
  - Poems, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Poems, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 17-30)
  - Poems, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - Poems, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 5-8)
  - Poems, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 9-12)
  - Poems, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 13-18)
  - Poems, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Poems, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Poems, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Poems, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Poems, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 24-25)
  - Poems, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 26-30)
  - Poems, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Poems, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Poems, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 4-8)
  - Poems, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 9-11)
  - Poems, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Poems, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Poems, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Poems, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Poems, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Poems, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Poems, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Poems, undated, A-D (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Poems, undated, F-H (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Poems, undated, I-M (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Poems, undated, N-On Ap (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Poems, undated, On A S-Pe (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Poems, undated, Ph-Pr (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Poems, undated, Pr-Rem (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Poems, undated, Ren-Sh (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Poems, undated, Si-So (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Poems, undated, Sp-Thi (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Poems, undated, Thu-We (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Poems, undated, Wh-Y (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Unpublished Manuscripts, Two Worlds in One [juvenile] (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
  - Unpublished Manuscripts, Manuscript [before 1956?] (Box 6, Folder 5-13)
  - Unpublished Manuscripts, The Mind Barefoot (Box 6, Folder 14-17)
  - Conference Entries with Criticism, Southwest Writers' Conference, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Contest Manuscript with Entry Rules, National Poetry Series 1979 Open Competition (Box 6, Folder 19-21)
  - Miscellaneous, 1963-undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Rough Drafts, 1973-1982 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Rough Drafts, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 24-25)
  - Rough Drafts, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Rough Drafts, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Rough Drafts, undated (Box 6, Folder 28-32)
- Short Stories, (552 leaves): (Box 7, Folder 1-38)
  Short stories are arranged alphabetically by title. Untitled stories and fragments are filed at the end of the series.
  - Autumn Come Silent (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Crack in the Armor (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - False Spring (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - The Funeral (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - The Girl who Wouldn't Do Anything (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - The Heavenly Hearing Aid (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - The Invasion (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Just Like Mama (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - The Lace Handkerchief (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - The Man who Got Away with Murder--Almost (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Merry Christmas, Mother Milton (Box 7, Folder 12-14)
  - Mr. Pomfret (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Miss Scaggs (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
  - The More Things Change (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Nobody but Becky (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - No Twelve Year Olds (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Pact (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - The Red Rooster (Box 7, Folder 22-23)
  - Shadow Before Me (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - The Shadows (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Tea Party (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Teashop Closed (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - The Terrible Music (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - A Time to Die (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - To Each his Own (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - To Tell the Truth (Box 7, Folder 31-32)
  - Tubby the Cub (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Under the Skin (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - The Voice (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - When the Starts Begin to Fall (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Untitled Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 37-38)
- Plays, (360 leaves): (Box 8, Folder 1-21)
  Plays are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - The Abs (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Huck Finn (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Jones Reversed (Box 8, Folder 3-8)
  - The Man Who Went Deaf (Box 8, Folder 9-12)
  - Peace, It's Wonderful (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Who Dropped Dead? (A Non-Musical Musical) (Box 8, Folder 14-21)
- Miscellaneous Works, (224 leaves, 1 item): (Box 8, Folder 22-40)
  Miscellaneous works include essays, reviews, and unidentified creative formats. Miscellaneous works are arranged alphabetically by title, or in a few cases, by format.
  - Article on Cynthia Macdonald (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - The Artist in the Christian Community (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Autobiography, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Book reviews (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - The Dialogue Sermon (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Easter and the Imagination (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Film reviews (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Jazz Mass Minus Music (Box 8, Folder 29-32)
  - Jazz Mass Minus Music, Some Observations On (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - A Poet's Eye View of Theology (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Letters and Papers from Prison (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - [Something to Clap About: A Folk Mass] (Box 8, Folder 36-37)
  - The Well-Made Poem, Id or Idn?t It? (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Why Poetry? (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 40)
- Published Works, (1139 leaves): (Box 9-10)
  Typescripts and proofs of published works are arranged chronologically by the year of publication of the finished work. For each publication, typescripts and proofs are arranged in order of their creation. Some of the typescripts and proofs are photocopies.
  - Adam's Footprint, Page proof (photocopy) (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - My Bones Being Wiser, Galley proof (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
  - Onions and Roses, Typescript (Box 9, Folder 4-7)
  - Onions and Roses, Galley proof (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - If I Could Sleep Deeply Enough, Typescript (Box 9, Folder 9-14)
  - If I Could Sleep Deeply Enough, Typescript (Photocopy) (Box 9, Folder 15-17)
  - If I Could Sleep Deeply Enough, Typescript (Box 9, Folder 18-20)
  - If I Could Sleep Deeply Enough, Typescript (Photocopy) (Box 9, Folder 21-22)
  - If I Could Sleep Deeply Enough, Galley proof (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - If I Could Sleep Deeply Enough, Rough set (Box 9, Folder 24-25)
  - If I Could Sleep Deeply Enough, Repro set (Box 9, Folder 26-27)
  - Selected and New Poems (The Sun has no History), Typescript (Box 10, Folder 1-5)
  - Selected and New Poems (The Sun has no History), Typescript (Photocopy except for 2nd page) (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Selected and New Poems (The Sun has no History), Typescript (Photocopy) (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
  - Selected and New Poems (The Sun has no History), Page proof, with corrections, (Photocopy) (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
  - Selected and New Poems, 1950-1980, Uncorrected proof copy (Photocopy) (Box 10, Folder 11-14)
  - Struggling to Swim on Concrete, Typescript (Box 10, Folder 15-19)
  - Struggling to Swim on Concrete, Galley proof (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Wage War on Silence, Typescript table of contents (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Wage War on Silence, Galley proof (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Wage War on Silence, Galley proof (Box 10, Folder 23)
- Writing Career, (244 leaves, 37 items): (Box 11, Oversize, Folder 1-32)
  Material in this series includes articles about Miller, financial and legal documents, items related to special events, reviews of Miller's work, etc. Materials in this series are arranged by subject.
  - Articles (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
  - Bibliography (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
  - Book Publicity (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Events, Annual Alumni Awards Banquet/ UH Alumni Organization, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Events, Chamber Music of Robert Avalon, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Events, Chamber Music of Robert Avalon, 1991 (Box Oversize)
  - Events, Houston Poetry Fest/Houston Center for the Humanities, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Events, Texas Women's Literary Tradition: Conference and a Celebration, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Events, A Tribute to Vassar Miller/Friends of the UH Libraries, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Events, Very Special Arts Festival, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 12-13)
  - Financial/Legal (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Music: Hymns with Thomas Avinger/Alec Wyton (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Poetry Submission Lists (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Receptions/Readings (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Reviews (Box 11, Folder 19-20)
- Personal, (62 leaves, 3 items): (Box 11, Folder 21-23)
  This series includes material relating to the churches attended by Miller, articles and other items collected as Issues about the Handicapped, and miscellaneous personal materials.
  - Churches (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Issues About the Handicapped (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 11, Folder 23)
- Photographs, (22 photographs): (Box 11, Oversize)
  Photographs are arranged in roughly chronological order.
  - 1962 and 1985, Photographers: Unidentified and Maud Lipscomb (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - 1985, Photographer: Maud Lipscomb (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - With Rev. Helen Havens, 1985, Photographer: Maud Lipscomb (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Very Special Arts Festival, 1985, Photographer: Maud Lipscomb (Box 11, Folder 27-32)
  - [Ca. 1983, Photographer: James Leifeste] (Box Oversize)
- Despite This Flesh Correspondence, (547 leaves, 3 items): (Box 12, Folder 1-27)
  This series contains correspondence related to the editing and publishing of the anthology Despite This Flesh. A major correspondent is University of Texas Press editor Suzanne Comer. Letters suggesting works for inclusion in the anthology, most of them solicited, are arranged separately at the beginning of this series, ordered alphabetically by author. General correspondence concerning the anthology is also ordered alphabetically by author. At the end of this series are permissions for publication, arranged separately by the name of the author of the work for which permission is being granted.
  - Suggestions for Anthology (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
  - B-Co (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Suzanne Comer (Box 12, Folder 5-8)
  - Co-Ho (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Hu-Mc (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Vassar Miller (Box 12, Folder 11-17)
  - N-Pr (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Pr-Sp (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Sp-We (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Wi-Wr (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - No Last Name (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Permissions (Box 12, Folder 23-27)
- Despite This Flesh Preparation, (228 leaves, 6 items): (Box 13, Folder 1-16)
  The material related to preparation of the anthology is arranged by subject, maintaining original order.
  - Author Addresses (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Short Story Index (Box 13, Folder 2-3)
  - Short Story Misc (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Fiction Catalog (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Poetry Index (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Grant Information (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - University of Texas Press (Box 13, Folder 8-9)
  - Choices for Anthology (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Articles and Review (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Old Literature of the Handicapped (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Old Literature of the Handicapped, Wells, H.G., The Time Machine (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Old Literature of the Handicapped, Dickens, Charles, Doctor Marigold (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Old Literature of the Handicapped, Kipling, Rudyard, They … (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Old Literature of the Handicapped, Tagore, Rabindranath, Vision (Box 13, Folder 16)
- Despite This Flesh Possibilities, (523 leaves, 12 items): (Box 13-14)
  The stories and poems which were labeled possibilities for the anthology are arranged with bound publications first, then single leaves. The single leaves are separated into two groupings or drafts, the second of which features line and word counts. Within each of these divisions, the bound publications or stories and poems are arranged alphabetically by author. Alphabetical order may not be exact in some sections in order to keep all of the pages in a short story together.
  - De Leeuw, David Birney (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Fahy, Christopher (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Hilberry, Conrad (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Jerome, Judson (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Prescott, Edgar (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Rilke, Rainer Maria (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Winner, Robert (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Katallagete (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Be-Do (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Beyers, Barbara L., By the Banks of the Brazos (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Bromfield, Louis, The Great Facade (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Ep-Ka (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Jacobson, Josephine, The Glen (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Ke-Li (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Ma-Mu (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Ni-Po (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Pritchett, V.S., Blind Love (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Ro-Si (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Shaw, Irwin, Whispers in Bedlam (Box 14, Folder 11-12)
  - St-Vl (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Wain, John, King Caliban (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - We-Wr (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Unidentified (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Line and Word Count (Box 14, Folder 17-27)
- Despite This Flesh Selections, (541 leaves, 13 items): (Box 15, Folder 1-31)
  The stories and poems which were labeled selections for the anthology are arranged in two groupings or drafts, each of which follows the organization which was adopted for the anthology. Alphabetical order may not be exact in some sections in order to keep all of the pages in a short story together.
  - Section Introductions (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Table of Contents (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Yoke in his Youth (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Counter, Original, Spare, Strange (Box 15, Folder 4-7)
  - Counter, Original, Spare, Strange: Farrington, Mark, Grandma When She Laughs (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - In Body, A Passenger and Rumpled (Box 15, Folder 9-10)
  - Beam in the Eye (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Beam in the Eye: Boyle, Kay, The Crazy Hunter. (Box 15, Folder 12-13)
  - Beam in the Eye (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Beam in the Eye: Wharton, Edith, The Young Gentlemen. (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Beam in the Eye (Box 15, Folder 16-17)
  - An Unrung Bell (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Yoke in his Youth (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - The Wrestled Angel (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Counter, Original, Spare, Strange (Box 15, Folder 21)
  - In Body, A Passenger and Rumpled (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - In Body, A Passenger and Rumpled: Boyle, Kay, The Crazy Hunter (Box 15, Folder 23-24)
  - In Body, A Passenger and Rumpled (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - In Body, A Passenger and Rumpled: Mann, Thomas, Little Herr Friedemann (Box 15, Folder 26)
  - In Body, A Passenger and Rumpled: Wharton, Edith, The Young Gentlemen (Box 15, Folder 27)
  - Beam in the Eye (Box 15, Folder 28)
  - An Unrung Bell: Pritchett, V.S., Blind Love (Box 15, Folder 29-30)
  - An Unrung Bell (Box 15, Folder 31)
- Despite This Flesh Drafts, (462 leaves, 2 items): (Box 16, Folder 1-27)
  There are three unedited drafts of the anthology, each of which follows the organization of the anthology.
  - Table of Contents, Yoke in his Youth (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - The Wrestled Angel (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - In Body, A Passenger and Rumpled (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Beam in the Eye (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - An Unrung Bell (Box 16, Folder 5-6)
  - Table of Contents, Introduction (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Yoke in his Youth (Box 16, Folder 8-9)
  - The Wrestled Angel (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - In Body, A Passenger and Rumpled (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Beam in the Eye (Box 16, Folder 12-14)
  - An Unrung Bell (Box 16, Folder 15-16)
  - An Unrung Bell (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Title, Table of Contents, Introduction (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Yoke in his Youth (Box 16, Folder 19-20)
  - The Wrestled Angel (Box 16, Folder 21)
  - In Body, A Passenger and Rumpled (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - Beam in the Eye (Box 16, Folder 23-25)
  - An Unrung Bell (Box 16, Folder 26-27)
- Despite This Flesh Copy-edited Draft, (230 leaves): (Box 17, Folder 1-12)
  There is one copy-edited draft, which follows the organization of the anthology.
  - Copyedited Draft (Box 17, Folder 1-11)
  - Copyedited Draft, Miscellaneous Pieces (Box 17, Folder 12)
- Despite This Flesh Galley Proof, (98 leaves): (Box 17, Folder 13-17)
  There is one galley proof, which follows the organization of the anthology.
  - Galley Proof (Box 17, Folder 13-17)